All right, בוקר טוב.
Boker Tov. So today's דף Daf is כ"ה, Kaf He, we pick
up at the top of כ"ה Kaf He and we are discussing
the issue, well the משנה Mishna deals with
cases of a marriage that has not been fully completed, אירוסין Eirusin
or שומרת יבם, Shomeret Yavam, and that those cases the woman can
go through the סוטה Sotah process in order to make her סוטה
Sotah קינוי Kinui and the סתירה, Stirah, forbidden to her husband, but
not in order to make her drink the water at the end.
And we are going to pick up today, we did raise in
the משנה Mishna important questions about the phenomenon about בית דין Beis
Din representing the husband and the questions raised about what would have
been the motivation for בית דין Beis Din to do that and
other questions about what type of evidence would have been necessary to
make a woman lose her כתובה Kesubah if she wasn't a סוטה,
Sotah, and interestingly both of those issues are going to be the
central focus of today's דף. Daf. Okay, so let's take a look
and that's really, really start with that exactly, centrally that topic, three
lines from the top, a brand new topic, so let's take a
look. איבעיא להו, Ibayahu, so they raised the following question: עוברת על
דת, Overas Al Das, a woman who transgresses the the the norm,
meaning the standard practices of modesty of married women. Now I want
to just I want to just clarify what this is, this is
a משנה Mishna in כתובות, Kesubos, a דת משה ודת יהודית, Das
Moshe VeDas Yehudis, and the issue here is not that she is
a sinner, the issue here is is that her behaviors impact her
the marriage. So for example, basically the משנה Mishna says that a
woman who transgresses דת משה, Das Moshe, biblical norms, laws, or דת
יהודית, Das Yehudis, or the practice of Jewish women, can be divorced
without a כתובה. Kesubah. And the point though is the גמרא Gemara
for example says what would be an example of עוברת על דת
משה? Overas Al Das Moshe? So it says a woman who for
example doesn't go to the מקוה Mikvah or a woman who feeds
her husband non-kosher food. What the גמרא Gemara does not say is
a woman who is מחלל שבת, Mechalel Shabbos, okay, a woman could
be מחלל שבת Mechalel Shabbos that is between her and God, that
is not a basis for the husband to divorce her. Now nowadays
we might say like if you're going to have the TV on
in the house on שבת, Shabbos, that impacts the nature of the
home on שבת, Shabbos, right? Or if you're going to cook the
food on שבת Shabbos and I can't eat it. But that, okay,
so there would be cases in which it would impact the marriage.
But if a woman goes ahead, I'm sorry not just I mean
whatever, sorry to point out that it's about the woman here, but
that's what it is, anyway not like men aren't מחלל שבת Mechalel
Shabbos either, anyway but if a woman goes ahead and decides that
she's going to go outdoors and and smoke or you know or
drive somewhere on שבת, Shabbos, that is not דת משה Das Moshe
in terms of a basis for divorce because that's just her sin,
it's between her and God, that is not a basis, that does
not impact the marriage. Okay, so it's a type of a transgression
that affects their married life together in a significant way. Similarly, עוברת
על דת Overas Al Das means a type of a behavior that
is seen to compromise the intimacy or the the quality of their
relationship and specifically it speaks about a number of behaviors that a
woman could do in public which basically are considered to be immodest
and therefore it sort of like winds up attracting the attention, the
unwanted attention of other men. And the so whether it is that
she is flirtatious with other men, I mean I'm sort of translating
it into a contemporary idiom because the גמרא Gemara talks about or
the משנה Mishna talks about just she like talks to strange men.
You know with us it's like what? Like she can't go out
and say like excuse me could you tell me like you know
but okay for us the you know, you know could you tell
me which way to get to so and so street? Oh you
talk to strange men. So you know but for them maybe the
norms were a little different or what would be considered problematic, but
I think to translate it in a contemporary idiom, let's say she's
being flirtatious with other men, or it talks about her you know
behaving in a way about in public that she's nursing her baby
or she's knitting, knitting in public, you know now we would say
breastfeeding in public, but anyway ways in which were seen as like
not just inappropriate but something that basically is getting that like you
know gets the unwanted attention, unwanted from the husband's perspective maybe from
her perspective as well, but whatever, of you know of other men.
So one of them is of course going with her hair uncovered
and so on. But these types of things which basically you know
impact the way in which the the intimacy of the relationship, the
way in which the husband sort of feels that you know doesn't
sort of garner his jealousy or bring another man even practically or
in somebody's imagination into the relationship. So those are the that's the
type of situations and we'll talk about it more when we get
to כתובות, Kesubos, but that's the type of issues that are considered
to be עוברת על דת. Overas Al Das. Okay, דת משה. Das
Moshe. That's the context of the idea of covering the hair and
so on. So the גמרא's Gemara now going to say so as
you could imagine this not so different from the סוטה Sotah idea.
The סוטה Sotah idea is something very concrete, right? If she committed
adultery there's no question she's forbidden to her husband, that's not a
question of just divorce without a כתובה. Kesubah. סוטה Sotah is a
woman that has suspected of that, but if that actually were true
she would be for completely הלכתית halachically forbidden, I mean even now
the תורה Torah forbids her, you know the הלכה Halacha forbids her
to have sex with her husband on the basis of this suspicion,
but it's based on... from the fact that sleeping with a man
makes her forbidden to her husband. But even without that reality, right,
if you know, you know, if he went into private with a
man and he wasn't warned by her husband, or she was doing
these things that are sort of in the same penumbra of this
whole experience, but it's not making her a סוטה Sotah because she
didn't actually secreted a man or there wasn't that suspicion yet, nevertheless,
it's certainly in this category of עוברת על דת, overes al das,
right? I mean it's the types of things that garner the husband's,
you know, that evoke the husband's jealousy and so on. So the
question is without making her forbidden to her husband, is it a
basis of divorce, you know, it would be a basis of divorce
without a כתובה. kesuvah. That's עוברת על דת. overes al das. Charlie,
what did you want to say? You had a question? Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So that was just
to explain those two words. איבעיא להו. Ibaiah lehu. עוברת על דת.
Overes al das. A woman who now crosses that line. צריכה התראה
להפסיד כתובתה ואינה צריכה. Tzerichah hasra'ah l'hafsid kesuvatah v'einah tzerichah. So when
we say that the husband can now divorce her, okay, interesting question
we'll get to is, must he divorce her? Okay, but now let's
just leave it as can. He can divorce her now without her
כתובה kesuvah because her behavior was inappropriate in terms of their relationship.
Okay, does she require warning? Does he need to say to her,
he or the בית דין, beis din, let's say he, need to
say to her, if I, if you do that again, I'm going
to divorce you without a כתובה? kesuvah? Okay, or you know, because
maybe like maybe she wasn't even aware she wasn't supposed to do
that, or maybe she was aware but didn't realize it was a
big deal or she didn't pay attention to the consequences. So would
we say that she needs warning or not for her to lose
her כתובה? kesuvah? Let's see how the גמרא Gemara frames the question.
מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, do we say כיון דעוברת על דת היא
לא בעי התראה? keivan d'overes al das hee lo ba'ei hasra'ah? Look,
bottom line, she acted in an inappropriate way, it compromised their relationship,
okay, and so she doesn't need warning. או דילמא, O dilma, or
do we say תבעי התראה, tiba'ei hasra'ah, she should. Why? דהדרא בה,
d'hadra bah,
because maybe if she's warned, maybe she'll change her practices, which is
interesting, which sort of frames it as it's not like right now
there's not a good enough basis, but it's sort of like, you
know,
does she deserve it? Like we didn't say, well she was שוגג,
shogeg, she doesn't deserve it. It's not, in terms of the practical
action she did right now, this would be appropriate. But maybe you
know, from a, you know, maybe we have a bigger picture type
of an approach. We don't want to, you know, we want to
encourage,
we don't want marriages to get break up so quickly. We want
to, we recognize that things often can be repaired and not every
mistake has to automatically lead to the most dire of consequences. If
we say divorce for without a כתובה, kesuvah, we are, A, making
it easier for the husband to divorce her just practically, he won't
have to pay. And B, we're communicating something about our about, you
know, about we're essentially the people, the rabbis who are making this
rule, are communicating that they think that she deserves to be divorced,
right? So is that necessarily the healthiest thing? Right? Maybe the healthiest
thing is no, like let's try to repair the situation first. Dov
had a question for us. So explaining this
was like a criminal matter in which התראה hasra'ah is one of
the
important...
Correct,
correct. It's not the warning, it's not like you can't get punished
without warning type of a thing. It's not a punishment, right? It's
also another thing. It's more like it's a fault divorce, okay? So
if she was to fault, she did something to hurt the marriage,
and she was at fault, right, so then the husband is free
from the obligation to pay the כתובה kesuvah because she's the reason
why they're getting divorced. So that's sort of how it's framed. It's
a type of thing. You're right, it's not like a punishment of
בית דין. beis din. So that's why the גמרא Gemara didn't say
like the התראה hasra'ah to make her מזיד meizid as opposed to
a שוגג. shogeg. It said because of these other concerns of like
maybe we don't want to rush to a divorce.
You had the way you framed it, I was still just asking
there's some cases where we do say you lose it, right? Like
for instance, let's say two witnesses said we actually saw her commit
adultery. We wouldn't say, oh well you know, maybe they can work
it out because it's to the marriage better to try to see
what you can do.
Right, because this isn't adultery. This is something that's more repairable. A,
besides the fact that besides the fact that okay, but besides the
fact that there's just the הלכה. halacha. The הלכה halacha is that
she's forbidden to her husband, we can't do anything about that הלכה,
halacha, okay? So here there isn't that הלכה, halacha, so there's more
to work with. Okay, but if you ask me also big picture
you can say some things we don't think are repairable, other things
we are. Now nowadays I think we do think that some of
those situations are repairable, right, okay? And that becomes an interesting issue
because like some people have been asking me about this, what happens
if a woman admits to committing adultery and so on, is there
a way, you know, and but they don't want to get divorced,
the husband wants to work it through, so there are ways of
dealing with that, okay? But anyway, from the גמרא's Gemara perspective, that's
not an option, okay, at least here it's not seeing that as
an option. Again, in הלכה halacha there's ways you sort of navigate
that because you technically don't believe her so unless there's real evidence
to it and so on, okay, but so A, yeah even if
we did want to repair it, there's the הלכתית halachic status that
can't be dealt with, and B, you know, there are some cases
that might be are not
are not repairable.
Right, but clearly, if she's going to sue for her כתובה, Ketubah,
he's going to have to bring evidence in court why he's not
obligated to pay. So it's not just his say so, if he
wants to get out of paying the כתובה, Ketubah, he's going to
have to bring evidence that she was עוברת על דת. Overet Al
Dat.
Okay, so you're asking if I understand like I could decide I
don't want my wife crocheting כיפות kippot in the שוק shuk and
you could decide it's no big deal that she's
crocheting in the שוק.
shuk. Is that true? No, the משנה Mishnah has a list of
objective criteria. Now, whether those change in different societies like מדברת עם
כל אדם medaberet im kol adam or whatever that might be. But
yes,
it gets to some of this question. Is it all בקפידא דבעל
תליא מילתא? bekapida debaal talya milta?
Right, so if he doesn't care, but then he wants to get
out of paying her כתובה Ketubah and then he claims he
does care, he can't say that. I understand, so we'll get to
that. But bottom line is that more what our גמרא's Gemara going
to look at today is even if she was עוברת על דת,
Overet Al Dat, can he sort of decide he's not מקפיד? makpid?
But his ability to say he's מקפיד makpid on something that we
haven't identified as an objective standard, obviously, would not be fair because
then he could just arbitrarily make her lose the כתובה. Ketubah. She's
entitled to the כתובה, Ketubah, so there has to be an objective
standard on the basis of which
that she could lose that. I do want to say something about
the שוגג shogeg issue and again about like that it doesn't say,
oh well, she was שוגג, shogeg, maybe it shouldn't be so bad.
Because at the end of the day, you could say, okay, who
cares whether she knew or didn't know? It sort of compromised the
relationship. Now, nevertheless, you could say, no, it compromises the relationship in
a different way if you know you're not supposed to do certain
behavior and you do it. Like, if you don't know, like, what
was so wrong? I was just whatever. But if it's oh well,
now actually, our standards are you don't do those types of things
and
whatever. So, the sense about how much is the relationship compromised does
sometimes impact whether the person is knowingly or unknowingly engaging in this
type of behavior. It is interesting, something interestingly I haven't mentioned since
the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, but it is interesting to ask
about a question of what happens in the case of סוטה Sotah
if she is a שוגג. shogeg. Now, what would be a case
of a שוגג shogeg if she's a סוטה? Sotah? Well, let's say,
I don't know, nobody ever told her that it was אסור assur
to sleep with another man. Okay. So, okay, so you could say
קרוב למזיד, karov lemeizid, everybody should know that, be aware of that.
So that's like an easier case to deal with. Okay, but there's
an interesting תשובה, teshuvah, I'm trying to remember who wrote it, about
a woman who basically
her husband was away and a man came to like, passing through
town, some charlatan, and he basically said that he was אליהו הנביא
Eliyahu Hanavi and he persuaded this woman to sleep with him and
he told her that if she would sleep with him then they
would then that would produce the משיח. Mashiach. And so she believed
him and she believed she had to, she was supposed to sleep
with him and she had to sleep with him and whatever and
she did so. And then the question was was she forbidden to
her husband? Okay, that's not just סוטה, Sotah, that's one who actually
slept with another man and I forget, I'd have to remember who
wrote this תשובה teshuvah but it's not recent, it's going back a
few hundred years. Anyway, the פוסק posek basically said that the פסוק
pasuk doesn't focus on the intentionality of the sin. It says כי
תשטה אשתו ומעלה בו מעל, Ki tisteh ishto umala bo maal,
that there was a sense that that actually was a wrong done
to the husband and a hurt to the relationship. And that's regardless
of whether the action was done in innocence or not in innocence,
to what the reality of that was in terms of her relationship
to her husband. So,
I think that's an interesting parallel, like here the גמרא Gemara does
not say that oh well, if she wasn't maybe you need התראה
hatra'ah because otherwise it didn't impact the relationship in the same way.
Right. Now again, I think there's a big difference between sleeping with
somebody
without realizing how wrong it is as opposed to, I don't know,
having some conversation or knitting in the marketplace. But nevertheless, it's interesting
that the גמרא Gemara doesn't frame it as like it was not
במזיד bemeizid and that's the issue. It frames it as like, okay,
but there's bigger picture, maybe we want to help repair the marriage.
Yes.
What if the woman is raped?
No, not if she's raped. But that's because that's completely not that's
again, that's not seen, there it was like volitional but not with
the intention of doing anything wrong, but it was volitional. And that's
seen as a different sort of... yeah.
But what about her human, like, I mean, there might be situations,
mental ill- found- Yeah, so right, right.
If she right, right, if it's like not intentional, right, if she's
not of right mind or she's not willing, it's a different story,
right. There was like sort of willing but it's not willing like
feeling that, believing it was permissible.
Well, isn't because in that situation there's also a wrong done to
the husband in a sense, right, like if if someone's wife...
Right, but she's not the one that did the wrong to him.
It's not, here it seems like she wronged him. Whatever how much
she felt she should have been doing it, she still, consciously, whatever,
she wronged him. Yes.
So דתי יהודית Dati Yehudit means norms regarding women or norms established
by...
It seems like it means established by women, you
know... Okay, so that's the question. So now we've gotten through four
lines of גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so okay, so the תוספות Tosafos so
interesting. Anyway, okay. או דילמא תיבעי התראה דהדר ביה תשובה, O dilma
tibei hatrah dihader bei teshuvah, or
no, she needs warning because maybe we want to help repair the
situation first. We don't want to run to divorce without a כתובה.
ketuvah. So תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. ארוסה ושומרת יבם
לא שותות ולא נוטלות כתובה. Arusah v'shomeret yavam lo shotot v'lo notlot
ketuvah. An ארוסה arusah and a שומרת יבם shomeret yavam don't drink
and don't get the כתובה, ketuvah, they
because
מדלא שתיה, mid'lo shatya, so they don't drink, but the first stage
of the process you do. That's why they don't get a כתובה.
ketuvah. הכינוי מקני לה, Hakinui mekanei lah, he does קינוי kinui and
makes her a סוטה sotah and therefore he winds up divorcing her
without a כתובה. ketuvah. למאי, L'mai, so why is he making her
a סוטה, sotah, right, what, what's the purpose of doing this קינוי
kinui and making her a סוטה? sotah? לאו לאפסודי כתובתה, Lav l'afsidei
ketuvatah, it must be to make her lose her כתובה. ketuvah. So
why do you need to go through, hey guy, hey buddy, if
your whole point is you're not going to be able to make
your wife drink the water, she's only an ארוסה. arusah. If you
want to make her lose the כתובה, ketuvah, so why do you
need to go through this process? Just bring witnesses that she's going
in private with other men, that she's going into seclusion with other
men. She doesn't, you don't need your warning. You don't need any
of that. The going into seclusion is clearly enough of an עוברת
על דת, overas al das, okay? So the fact that that wasn't
enough, the fact of her going into seclusion, that he needed to
do the קינוי kinui shows that if she's going to lose her
כתובה, ketuvah, there needs to be some warning. Okay, now it's interesting.
It might not actually be the warning that turns her into a
סוטה, sotah, but the גמרא Gemara is sort of saying regardless, it's
not enough that she went into seclusion, okay? So הכינוי hakinui assumes
התראה hatrah here.
Yeah, קינוי kinui winds
up becoming a form of התראה, hatrah, okay? So it says ah,
so look, you see the going into seclusion is not enough. Clearly
the only reason he would do קינוי kinui would be to make
her lose the כתובה. ketuvah. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, לא, לאוסרה עליו. lo, le'osrah alav. No, there's other
things that are accomplished, because maybe if she just went into seclusion,
she'd lose the כתובה, ketuvah, but he's doing the קינוי kinui because
he wants to make her into a סוטה. sotah. He wants to
make her forbidden, forbidden on him now. Why does he want to
make her forbidden on him? Like, you know, because maybe he feels
like, you know, he's so angry, like it says, if you don't
want to have sex with her, don't have sex with her, but
I don't know, he's so angry at her, whatever, he wants to
just impose this status on her. You know, put the big red
letter S on her, or סמך Samech or whatever, you know, make
her into a סוטה. sotah. It's not just about the כתובה, ketuvah,
that she would lose anyway, but he wants to give, make her
forbidden on him. Okay, רב פפא אמר, Rav Papa amar, להשקותה כשינשאו.
lehashkosah k'sheyinasu. No, no, no, actually there would be an opportunity that
he could actually make her drink the water. He warns her when
she's an ארוסה arusah for the situation that now if she were
to go into private after נישואין, nisuin, he would still on the
basis of that early warning be able to make her drink. So
he can't make her drink as an ארוסה, arusah, but if she
went into seclusion afterwards, he could make her drink.
He can do the קינוי kinui and then they can have נישואין
nisuin and then get married?
Yes, but it can't be קינוי, kinui, סתירה, stirah, and נישואין nisuin
because then he would have had sex with her after she had
been a סוטה sotah and then it wouldn't be וניקה האיש מעון.
v'nikah ha'ish me'avon. But it could be קינוי, kinui, נישואין, nisuin, סתירה
stirah and that she'd be a סוטה. sotah. Yep. So why is
he going through with the נישואין nisuin after the קינוי? kinui? Oh
no, I'm just keeping my bases covered, right? Why, now we can
get married, she's been warned, so it'll all be good. Okay, anyway,
so that's why he's doing it, להשקותה כשינשאו. lehashkosah k'sheyinasu. כדתניא, K'detanya,
אין מקנא לארוסה להשקותה כשהיא ארוסה, ein mekanei l'arusah lehashkosah k'shehi arusah,
he can't do the drink her water while she's an ארוסה, arusah,
אבל מקנא לארוסה להשקותה כשינשאו. aval mekanei l'arusah lehashkosah k'sheyinasu. He could
do it so if she goes in private when she's in נישואין,
nisuin, then she could become a סוטה sotah on the basis of
that. So you can't prove anything from that. She could have lost
her כתובה ketuvah just by going in seclusion, the purpose of the
קינוי kinui was something else. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, let's try again.
תא שמע, Ta shema, אלמנה כהן גדול גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט, amanah
kohen gadol gerushah vachallutzah l'kohen hedyot, all these cases in the משנה
mishnah where a woman is forbidden on her, where the marriage is
forbidden but still binding, okay? ממזרת ונתינה לישראל בת ישראל לממזר ולנתין.
mamzeres u'nesina l'yisrael bas Yisrael l'mamzer u'lenasin. All these cases of the
איסורי לאוין issurei lavin where the, where again, it's a biblical prohibition
but the marriage is binding. לא שותות ולא נוטלות כתובה, Lo shosos
v'lo notlos kesuvah, they don't drink and they don't get their כתובה.
ketuvah. Now, מדלא שתיה, mid'lo shatya, so they're not, so again, they're
not being forced to drink, הכינוי מקני לה, hakinui mekanei lah, but
the point still is that he's going, he can go through this
process of קינוי. kinui. Now, again, the question is, ולמאי, u'lemai, what's
the purpose? אי לאוסרה עליו, Ei le'osrah alav, now you can't give
the answer, oh, well, he's warning her to make her a סוטה
sotah to make her forbidden. No, האי איסורא דקאי, hai issura d'ka'i,
he's already forbidden to, there's already a לאו lav for them to
continue to have sex because she's a גרושה gerushah or whatever the
case might be and he's a כהן. kohen. So that answer doesn't
work. אלא לאו, Ella lav, לאפסודי כתובתה. l'afsidei kesuvatah. So why, it
must be that the purpose of doing קינוי kinui is to make
them lose the כתובה ketuvah and it's not enough that she just
went into seclusion, okay? And you can't give the other answer, both
of the previous answers, it's a brilliant point, both of the previous
answers are not relevant. לאוסרה עליו Le'osrah alav isn't relevant, she's already
forbidden, and להשקותה כשינשאו lehashkosah k'sheyinasu isn't relevant because it's already נישואין.
nisuin. Now, they're already נישואין, nisuin, right, it's just that it's
an איסור issur גרושה gerushah to
a
כהן. kohen. Exactly.
Exactly. Because it wasn't enough that she went into seclusion. Exactly. So
exactly, so that's the point. All these cases, why do you need
קינוי? Kinui? She went into seclusion with a strange man, that should
suffice to make her lose her כתובה. Kesuvah. Okay. So אמר רב
יהודה מדסקרתא, Amar Rav Yehuda mi-Diskarta, לא, lo, לאסרה לבועל כבעל. le'osrah
labo'el k'ba'al. No, and this makes more sense than לאסרה עליו. le'osrah
alav. He wants to make her into a סוטה Sotah so that
if and when they get divorced or he dies, she remains forbidden
on the guy that she's suspected of committing adultery with. Okay? Because
a סוטה, Sotah, a woman who actually sleeps with another man is
forbidden on her husband and forbidden to continue to have sex with
the man she slept with, and similarly, a woman who is a
ספק סוטה Safek Sotah in that state of being suspected is forbidden
to have sex with her husband and even then if the husband
died, if she remained divorced, if she remains a סוטה, Sotah, right,
she is then forbidden to have sex with that guy. Actually, it's
an interesting question. Let's say he makes her a סוטה, Sotah, does
not get around to bringing her to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
divorces her, she never has an opportunity to prove her innocence, right,
because he never brought her to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, can't
do it now that they're divorced, and she remains forbidden on this
other guy that she was suspected of. So, like I don't know,
right, imagine that she actually was, I don't know, was having, you
know, had some flirtation with this guy but didn't sleep with him
and now she's divorced and she actually wants to marry this other
guy. Now she's forbidden because the husband made her a סוטה Sotah
and she doesn't have the opportunity. So, you know, it's pretty interesting
that he has this power to make her forbidden on this man
even if she didn't actually sleep with him.
If they went through the whole thing and she came out clean,
then she can be with him.
Yeah, right, clearly if there was nothing going on.
Exactly. That only kicks in if he makes her a סוטה, Sotah,
right, not if he divorces her without a כתובה Kesuvah with suspicion
then. Correct.
Correct. Correct. So that's what it's saying. If he just had suspicions
and was עוברת על דת overes al das and he divorced her,
she could go marry this other man. But he is saying to
himself, I'm going to divorce her and make sure that she doesn't
wind up marrying this guy. Like I know that she's been flirting
with her high school boyfriend, and whether she's having sex with him
or not, I'm going to ensure she's never going to marry him.
So I'm going to do this thing and warn her, and therefore
I'll divorce her and she won't be able to. So right, I
could have divorced her without her כתובה Kesuvah anyway, but now I'm
making this guy off limits.
Yeah, and then again, the גט Get has to free her absolutely.
She is totally freed from me, she's just not, you're saying she's
not like מותרת לכל אדם. mutteres lechol adam. Yeah, but not based
on, not based on a connection to the husband, yes.
There's something really interesting from like, like in the jurisprudence here. Usually,
you need warning that's connected to a certain outcome. Here, the outcome
is the same outcome, but what determines התראה Hasra'ah not is his
motivation or his mindset.
What are you talking about? No. No. It's just a question about
what, no,
we're just trying to figure out what motivated him. The point is
and bring it as evidence. We're trying to say it must be
that you need התראה Hasra'ah because or else why would he have
bothered to do התראה? Hasra'ah? And the answer is no. You don't
need התראה Hasra'ah for her to lose her כתובה. Kesuvah. Why is
he bothering to do התראה Hasra'ah for a different outcome? For the
outcome of to make her forbidden on the husband. But at the
end of the day his motivation, on the guy. But at the
end of the day his motivation doesn't matter. You say what, if
you want to frame it another way, don't say why is he
doing it, say what is achieved by the התראה? Hasra'ah? What does
התראה Hasra'ah accomplish? It doesn't necessarily accomplish her losing her כתובה, Kesuvah,
that was already achieved. What it accomplishes is it makes her forbidden
on the other guy. דתנן, Detnan, taught in a משנה, Mishnah, כשם
שאסורה לבעל כך אסורה לבועל. Keshem she'assura laba'al kach assura labo'el. Okay,
so that's what it accomplishes. That's why the קינוי Kinui plays a
role here and the קינוי Kinui is not necessary for making her
lose her כתובה. Kesuvah. So we still haven't proven whether you need
התראה Hasra'ah to make her lose her כתובה. Kesuvah. אמר רבי חנינא
מסורא, Amar Rabi Chanina mi-Sura, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear,
ואלו שבית דין מקנאין להן. v'eilu she'Beis Din m'kana'in lahen. Now we're
going to move on to the בית דין. Beis Din. מי שנתחרש
בעלה, Mi shenischaresh ba'alah, her husband became a deaf-mute, או נשתטה, o
nishtateh, or he became like insane, mentally ill, או שהיה חבוש בבית
האסורין, o shehayah chavush b'veis ha'asurin, or he's in prison, ולא להשקותה
אמרו. v'lo le'ashkosah amru. And now the משנה Mishnah spells out why
is בית דין Beis Din doing this. It is not, they're not
doing it to enable him to make her drink,
אלא, ella, but for the purpose לפוסלה מכתובתה, lifoslah miksuvashah, to make
her lose her כתובה. Kesuvah. It didn't say they're doing it to
make her אסורה assura to the husband, right? That could have said
that, right? It didn't, you know, it said they're doing it for
the purpose of making her lose her כתובה. Kesuvah. So that's pretty
clear. It sounds like there would be no other way she could
lose her כתובה Kesuvah other than this. שמע מינה בעי התראה שמע
מינה. Shma mina ba'ei hasra'ah shma mina. So the question is, why
did they have to do that? If all they're trying to do
is make her lose her כתובה, Kesuvah, just get witnesses that she's
Maybe they
were trying to grease the skids to try to get them to
divorce by making her אסור assur to him and by making her
אסור assur to him it's just ensuring that they'll get divorced. But
the גמרא Gemara says, but you can't speculate about that or you
can't say that's the reason because it specifically says they're doing it
for the sake of making her lose her כתובה. kesuva. So it's
identifying that that is what's accomplished by them doing this, which makes
it sound like otherwise she wouldn't lose her כתובה. kesuva. Plus, since
why not? Isn't there evidence? Just get evidence that she went into
into seclusion. So you see that a woman who's עוברת על דת
overes al das it's not sufficient. There needs to actually be a
form of warning. Now again, that warning doesn't have to be the
type of a warning that makes her a סוטה, sotah, right? Because
if you say I don't want to see you talking to strange
men she doesn't become a סוטה, sotah, that's also an עוברת על
דת. overes al das. Okay, but but whatever the עוברת על דת
overes al das is, it needs a warning in order for her
to lose her כתובה. kesuva.
Yes. What if we can't accept that this this this being and
the the husband's out of it in whatever way? Like he's not
around to have a suspicion like based on דת משה. das Moshe.
Right. So it's like this I don't know that you can apply
that situation.
I'm sorry so what are you saying?
Because this is a different system, that in the other situation there's
a husband there who could be suspicious. Right.
So so that's going to be the next line of the גמרא.
Gemara. Excellent. So that's the next line of the גמרא. Gemara. Let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: It says
וכולו מאי טעמא לא אמרי מהא. Vechulu mai taama lo amri meha.
So why why don't we just start with this? This was such
a good proof. It explicitly says לאפסודה כתובתה, leafasida kesuvassa, which makes
it clear that there was no other way for her to lose
her כתובה. kesuva. Of course the nice thing is this allowed us
a
build-up anyway fine doesn't
matter it gives the גמרא Gemara an opportunity to make Jannah's point.
So it says No, דילמא שאני התם דלית לה אינשא דבעל כלל.
Dilma shani hasam d'lais lah insa d'baal klal. No, because in we
might you could say there she doesn't lose her כתובה kesuva without
warning because she's not her husband isn't around. So naturally her behavior
will be a little bit more loose, she'll take less care of
her behavior and so on. And therefore she cannot it's an interesting
bit, which way would you have argued that, but it's saying you
could argue that therefore doing this behavior is not as bad because
it's not so much in defiance of her husband because her husband
isn't around. So therefore in this case to make the behavior worse
she needs the warning. But in case where her husband is around
and she normally would be more constrained and she still does this,
then that's so bad that even without warning. So you could have
made that distinction. We don't say that. Right. Okay, exactly. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay. איבעיא להו. Iba'u lehu.
So that was question number one. Does she need warning for עוברת
על דת? overes al das? Answer is yes. What's really fascinating again,
right? We're going to learn in כתובות Ksuvos a whole פרק perek
that focuses on or section of a פרק perek that focuses on
עוברת על דת overes al das and this basic question which is
what how do you prove what type of evidence or warning or
whatever isn't in כתובות, Ksuvos, it's here. Okay. So this is really
like a necessary I mean we know why we're discussing it here
but it's almost like a necessary clarification of a סוגיא sugya in
כתובות. Ksuvos. Okay, איבעיא להו. Iba'u lehu. They raised the following question:
עוברת על דת ורצה בעל לקיימה מקיימה או אינו מקיימה? Overes al
das veratza baal lekayma mekayma o eino mekayma? This is almost a
more important question which also shockingly isn't in כתובות. Ksuvos. Should this
woman is acting in this way, behavior which is seen to be
as inappropriate and violating norms of modesty and so on, is the
husband if he says it's okay with me? Or if not it's
okay with me but I'm not interested in divorcing her on the
basis of this. Okay, is he allowed to is he allowed to
do this or do we say this is an unhealthy marriage? Like
you know either we're concerned for your marriage or concerned for the
general marriages in society and we do not want to allow this
type of a marriage to remain as an as a you know
as seen as acceptable and we are going to demand that that
you guys get divorced. Okay, so that's the question.
מי אמרינן Mi amrinan do we say בקפידא דבעל תלא רחמנא bekfeida
debaal tala rachmana and he doesn't mind, לא קפיד? lo kapid? It's
an interesting phrase תלא רחמנא tala rachmana because it's like echoing a
סוטה sotah case but this is not exactly סוטה. sotah. Do we
say it's about the husband's like sort of being קפידא? kfeida? What's
a good English word for קפידא? kfeida? Concern,
but his like what bothers
him. Not anxiety. How do they translate that קפידא? kfeida? His the
things that he's מקפיד makpid on, that he's like insistent on, what?
Maybe use the word objection.
Objection. Okay. It's a little bit more than an objection. It's like
deep down it bothers me. Like I find it objectionable. Okay, that's
maybe a little bit better. Anyway, but it's about the husband not
not wanting it, you know, and being upset about it. והא לא
קפיד, vehalo kapid, he's not upset about it. So bottom line is
this just this just entitles him to divorce her without a כתובה
kesuva because because she has wronged him and it's a fault divorce
so it allows him to do so because because... if it bothers
him, okay, if it impacts the marriage. But if it doesn't bother
him or whatever, he's not forced to end the marriage. או דילמא
כיוון דקא קפיד קפיד, O dilma keivan deka kapid kapid, or do
we say, now that's a funny phrase, since it bothers him, it
bothers him. You just said it didn't bother him. So what Rashi
says is, no, that since it should bother him, it matters, okay,
which case, which case, okay, which again you could read that in
two ways. You could read that that he might say it doesn't
bother him, but like deep down we know that it does and
we're going to say that this is unhealthy for this marriage to
continue, right? Or do we say, another way of saying it is
again, like no, actually this is unhealthy because for society, because we
don't want to be sending a message that these types of behaviors
are acceptable, okay?
So this is something that we deem objectionable to anybody even if
he doesn't mind it.
Exactly, it's an objectionable behavior and therefore whether it's objectionable to him
or not we need to object to it. Again, it's so fascinating
right, because obviously for us some of this is so
bizarre, like it seems very, I don't know what the right phrase
is, paternalistic or controlling, like that the court system would decide whether
couples should remain married or not remain married. But you know, hello,
I mean they're going to decide if a woman's a סוטה, Sotah,
if a woman's whatever, הלכה halacha does determine like whether this marriage
can continue or not and בית דין Beis Din gets involved in
it and so on. So here, even though there's not a הלכה
halachic reason that she's objectively forbidden or that the marriage is objectively
forbidden like a כהן Kohen and a גרושה, grusha, בית דין Beis
Din sees that their role is to, you know, is to play
this type of a role in society.
And getting involved in who gets married to whom.
Okay, it's a little bit of a different point, but I take
your point, yes.
But in secular law, at least in the United States, the idea
that a couple can simply agree to get divorced is really something
in the last two generations.
Yes, that we might, that's the opposite, that we might,
it is the opposite, that's right.
That there's a, that we require, that we have an idea of
no fault divorce or do we have such an investment in sort
of marriage and so on that we don't allow it to be
easily dissolved, right? So that's the idea of fault or no fault
divorce, which is true, it's like we're making a judgment of what's
healthy for society and therefore we're making it easier or harder for
them to get out of it. But this is going, we're making
a judgment what's better for society and therefore we're going to force
them to get out of it. So it's a little bit, but
you're right, I mean ultimately, you know, some of these
rules are for the betterment of society. Anyway, that's the question, are
we asking because deep down we think it's in his best interest
and he's just not being honest with himself, or is it more
of a broader societal point?
You're making him psychologically lacking almost in a similar way to the
חרש cheresh lacking.
Oh, that's interesting. Like the בית דין Beis Din taking the role
of the חרש, cheresh, here he's like yeah, we're going to have
to step in for you because you're, you know, you're not being
able to be objective here. You
don't realize how much your marriage is being destroyed right now, or
whatever the case might be. Yeah.
Is the גמרא Gemara making any kind of statement about like when
we say someone's like מקפיד makpid or not מקפיד makpid in general?
That's a religious value. In other words, it casts aspersions on the
possibility that someone need not be
מקפיד makpid about...
I don't think we can generalize, I mean in this context...
in this context,
yeah, in this context, I mean the גמרא Gemara in כתובות Kesubos
discusses that about what, I mean in a way we sort of
saw it before also, that whether it's a מצוה לקנאות mitzvah lekannos
or רשות לקנאות, reshus lekannos, like what, you know you could ask
the same thing about parenting, right? What's the right balance between being
strict and being tolerant and at what stage, you know? Yeah, so
that's the question that it's asking. Okay,
maybe parenting isn't a great place...
where I mean the גמרא Gemara also assumes not societal norms but
personal norms, for example, פלניא הכי. pelanya hachi.
Right, exactly. Okay, so it says תא שמע. ta shema. So that's
what we want to know, if he's okay with it, are we
okay with it? ואלו שבית דין מקנאים להן, ve'eilu she'Beis Din mekannim
lahen, בית דין Beis Din steps in, so there you go, whoever
made that point. מי שנתחרש בעלה... mi she'nischaraish ba'alah... oh wow, או
נשתטה, o nishtateh, או שהיה חבוש בבית
האסורין.
o shehayah
chavush b'veis ha'asurin. So בית
דין Beis Din is going to step in. אי אמרת רצה בעל
לקיים מקיים, ei amart ratzah ba'al lekayem mekayem, if the husband can
choose to be okay with it, so עבדי בית דין מידי דדילמא
לא ניחא ליה לבעל? avdi Beis Din midi d'dilma lo nicha lei
leba'al? Why will the בית דין Beis Din step in? The husband
might get better or he might get freed from prison and then
they'll have worked against his interests. So how can they necessarily step
in and act on behalf of his interests if this might not
be his interests? He might not want this. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, סתמא דמילתא. stama demilsa. No, we could
say כיוון דעברת אדת, keivan de'avras adas, since she violated these norms,
ניחא ליה, nicha lei, it is in his interest. So just because
we're saying that there are times that he could choose to be
okay with it, we could still act on his behalf based on
what is the norm. So that doesn't prove one way or the
other. Okay, so we don't know the answer to that, whether רצה
לקיים מקיים ratzah lekayem mekayem or not, but based on the ongoing
discussion we're going to implicitly answer that question. At this stage we
don't yet know the answer. איבעיא להו. Ibaiah lehu. Now we have
the following question. בעל שמחל על קינויו קינויו מחול או אינו מחול?
Ba'al shemachal al kinnuyo, kinnuyo machul o eino machul? Okay,
now here this is a question that actually is not about עוברת
על דת, overes al das, or could be, but it's more direct...
or more immediately about the question of a סוטה. Sotah. The husband
is מקנא mekaneh his wife, okay, and then he says, you know
what, forget about that קינוי, kinuy, I don't want to get you
in trouble, I understand, whatever, sometimes you're busy, you have to go
into, you have to go into his private office, whatever.
Hotel. Whatever. Okay. Whatever. Anyway, I מוחל mochel on the קינוי. kinuy.
And then she goes ahead and she goes in private. Can he
remove the קינוי, kinuy, or once he made it, she becomes a
סוטה? Sotah? Just to make it a little bit more challenging, can
he remove the קינוי kinuy after she went in private? Okay. So
she became a סוטה Sotah and says, you know what, I retroactively
retract my קינוי. kinuy. Okay. So can he do it? Okay. But
first let's deal with the easier case, even before she goes in
private. What's the story? מי אמרינן דכינוי דבעל תלה רחמנא ובעל הא
מחיל ליה? Mi amrinan dekinuy deba'al talah Rachmana uba'al ha machil leh?
Now we understand the phrase תלה רחמנא, talah Rachmana, because now we're
dealing with the סוטה Sotah category, not with the עוברת על דת
overes al das category. Ultimately it's because he was jealous, he was
upset, he objected, and when he stops objecting, the whole thing falls
off. Okay. מחיל ליה לקינויה. machil leh lekinuyeh. או דילמא כיון דקני
ליה מעיקרא לא מצי מחיל ליה? O dilma keivan dekani leh me'ikara
lo matzi machil leh? No, he warned her, he can't retract it.
Now, it doesn't exactly explain what the other side is. The other
side could just be it's a formal rule, it might have started
to be about your objection, but once you've created facts on the
ground, you're not empowered to retract. But more interestingly, we could go
back to points we made at the beginning of the מסכת, masechet,
which is how much is it sort of following the biblical model
of וקנא את אשתו vekinah et ishto and it's all an outgrowth
of his jealousy and הקפדה hakpadah and objection etc., or how much
is it based on how the גמרא Gemara has made it a
legal issue, brought in witnesses and a court and רגלים לדבר, raglayim
ladavar, and there's actually objective ground for suspicion. So we could say,
it's very nice that you have—it has stopped bothering you. But the
fact that you warned her shows that there was something there that
was upsetting you. And the fact that she went ahead and went
in private, once again, that creates a רגלים לדבר, raglayim ladavar, and
it doesn't matter if it's no longer bothering you, you know, we're
taking over from here, these are objective realities of רגלים לדבר. raglayim
ladavar. So that's I would say maybe the other way of thinking
about it, right? How much is it about him, and how much
is it about just creating רגלים לדבר? raglayim ladavar? Right? An interesting
question is, you know, what happens if for example, let's take another
case, a woman is raped, or somebody is, I don't know, assaulted,
and they refuse to press charges. So technically speaking, who cares that
they refuse to press charges? It was a crime against, you know,
it was a crime of the state, right? Whether—it's not this person
gets to decide, it's not—it's not just, you know, because it's—it's about
him, right? It's—I mean, yes, a violence was done to this person,
but whether the person itself wants to be מוחל mochel or not,
the state could decide to go—to go ahead and press charges regardless,
right?
Where that—yes? Okay. It's just—it's very hard, because if the person doesn't
show up at court and testifying or whatever. Okay. So you could
say it doesn't matter, you know, it's not about your הקפדה, hakpadah,
right? It's about crime against society, right? It's a—what's true?
Crime against society, it's an objective thing against society.
Right, exactly. So let's—anyway, it's a fascinating question about whether he can
choose, you know, to be מוחל mochel or not. How much is
it about the רגלים לדבר, raglayim ladavar, the objective reality, and how
much is it about his—his, you know, what was done to him
and his objection and so on. תא שמע. Ta shema. This is
such a great דף. daf. It is. ואלו שבית דין מקנאין להן
מי שנתחרש בעלה או נשתטה או שהיה חבוש בבית האסורין. Ve'elu sheBeit
Din meknain lahen, mi shenitcharesh ba'alah o nishtatah o shehayah chavush beveit
ha'asurin. Okay,
fine. So בית דין's Beit Din going to step in and do
it for him. ואי אמרת בעל שמחל על קינויו קינויו
מחול—but Ve'i amart ba'al shemachal al kinuyo kinuyo machul if the husband
can retract his own קינוי, kinuy, this thing that בית דין Beit
Din did is considered to be his קינוי. kinuy. They're seen as
operating on his behalf. Okay. So now they did it for him.
So therefore what? עבדינן מידי דאתי בעל ומחיל ליה? Avdinan midi de'ati
ba'al umachil leh? Why would we do something that the husband could
retract? Why not? Actually, that's great. We'll do it. If he doesn't
like it, he can retract it. But the גמרא's—but Gemara the גמרא's
Gemara concern is that will undermine the authority of בית דין. Beit
Din. We'll have done it, and he'll negate what we did. So
the גמרא Gemara says we're not concerned about that. סתמא דמילתא מסתפי
ומסקי כבי דינא. Stama demilta mistafi umaski keBeit Dina. No on the
way—it's funny. We're doing it because we assume it's what he wants,
and then he'll go along with it because he'll generally go along
with what we do.
So generally the presumption will be that nine times out of ten
a person won't want to
un—but that's not what the גמרא Gemara says. No, the גמרא Gemara
could have said סתמא דמילתא stama demilta a husband is מקפיד makpid
and he won't be מוחל. mochel. But it says סתמא דמילתא stama
demilta he'll go along with it because he'll follow our lead. That's
what it says, he'll follow—so it's like a little bit circular, right?
We're empowered to do it because we assume that a normal husband
would want to be מוחל—I mochel mean would want to be—would want
to be מקנא. mekaneh. And once we step in, then even if
he was in that middle camp, he'll most likely follow our lead
anyway, so we don't have to worry.
He'll agree. מסקי. Maski. Right. It's not like he'll accept it even
though grudgingly.
I didn't—I didn't say grudgingly. Okay. Following the lead. That's what מסקי
maski is. We lead the way, and he follows. Okay. It doesn't
say—so anyway, so it is—I mean that is how things work, right?
It is true that that's the— Wait, so Milicamp, he'll most likely
follow our lead anyway so we don't have to worry. But I
agree, מסכים. maskim. Right. It's not like he'll object, even though grudgingly.
I didn't say grudgingly. I said following the lead. That's what מסכים
maskim is. We lead the way and he follows, okay? It doesn't
say—so anyway, so it is interest—I mean, that is how these things
work, right? It is true that that's the norm, but even if
he was ambivalent, once we stepped in, that'll help push him into
that norm, okay? So anyway, so we don't know the answer. We
don't know the answer if—if he can be מוחל mochal on the
קינוי kinuy and we don't know the answer if—what was the other
question about? Oh, if he can choose to just keep on living
with her regardless.
Was that the other question?
Wait, where are we? We need right. Okay,
right. So now it says like this. Where are we? תא שמע,
ta shema, come in here. ומוסרין לו שני תלמידי חכמים שמא יבא
עליה
בדרך. u-mosrin lo shnei talmidei chachamim shema yavo aleha ba-derech. So when
they—remember when he's bringing her to בית דין, beit din, you give
there the two scholars to accompany them so that they won't have
sex. ואי אמרת בעל שמחל על קינויו קינויו מחול, ve-i amarta ba'al
she-machal al kinuyo kinuyo machul, but if he could reverse his קינוי—and
kinuy now we're assuming even after she became a
סוטה—so sotah why are we so concerned that they might, you know,
have, you know, have the יצר הרע yetzer hara get the better
of them and they decide to have sex? They have a way
that they could actually do it בהיתר. be-heter. ליכלי וליקנייה וליבעול. lichli
ve-likniyah ve-livol.
So go ahead, remove your קינוי, kinuy, have sex, save us from
the whole problem of the whole proceeding, יישר כוח. yashar koach. So
why are we so concerned to protect against that? Actually, there's a
בהיתר be-heter way of doing it. So הגמרא ha-gemara says, yeah, actually,
maybe that's why we're sending them with the תורה torah scholars. מה
ישנא תלמידי חכמים? mah ishna talmidei chachamim? Why are we דוקא davka
sending them scholars? דגמירי, degamiri, because they know the הלכה. halacha. דאי
בעו למבעל, de-i bau lemival, so then they can realize that if
it looks like he's they're interested in having sex, they'll tell him
how to do it in a בהיתר be-heter way. אמר ליה אחיל
לקינויך ובעול, amar leh achil le-kinuyacha u-veol, so they'll tell him, fine,
just remove your קינוי. kinuy. So it's not that we're trying to
prevent it at all costs, we're actually trying to make sure that
whatever decision they make is the right decision. Okay, so we still
don't know if he can revoke his קינוי. kinuy. תא שמע, ta
shema, come in here.
Wait, so we have just proof?
No, how have we proof?
Why? Because the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim can say you
can—so there's two ways of explaining it. Either they go with him
to ensure that he doesn't have sex or they don't have sex
under any circumstances, even if he revokes his קינוי kinuy they tell
him that he's not allowed to, or they go with him to
instruct him how he can by removing his
קינוי. kinuy. תא שמע דאמר רבי אושעיא, ta shema de-amar rabbi oshaya,
שלושה דברים סחו לי צעירי מאנשי ירושלים, shlosha devarim sachu li tze'irei
me-anshei yerushalayim, צעירי tze'irei of the people of ירושלים yerushalayim whispered to
me three things. Number one, בעל שמחל על קינויו קינויו מחול. ba'al
she-machal al kinuyo kinuyo machul. There you go. The husband can revoke
his קינוי. kinuy. Okay, and then we're going to discuss in a
minute even after she becomes a סוטה. sotah. Number two, וזקן ממרא
שרצו בית דין למחול לו מוחלין לו. ve-zaken mamre she-ratzu beit din
limchol lo mochlin lo. If the בית דין beit din wants to
forgo the זקן ממרא, zaken mamre, the person who acts in defiance
of the court and פוסקן pasken opposite of the court, they can
forgo. Now this is really such a great comparison because defying, right,
the authority of the court is not just the כבוד kavod of
the personal כבוד kavod of the court that they could be מוחל,
mochal, it's about the, you know, the authority of the institution. The
institution's authority is being undermined by that there's this defiant person פוסקן
pasken in opposition and nobody is doing anything about it. So, right,
so you know, so there you have to—since when is it the
personal decision of the court? Right, that's an institution that has to
be protected. So you could ask the same thing about the marriage.
Since when is it the personal decision of the husband? The institution
of marriage has to be respected, but obviously there's a big difference.
One is a court for all of society, one is their own
personal marriage, even though other people might look at their marriage and
learn from it, right? So this is the question: how much is
it about the particular people involved, how much is it about the
institution? So he's saying in all these cases you could be מוחל.
mochal. מוחל mochal on the קינוי, kinuy, מוחל mochal on the זקן
ממרא, zaken mamre, and ובן סורר ומורה שרצו אביו ואמו למחול מוחלין
לו. u-ven sorer u-moreh she-ratzu aviv ve-imo limchol mochlin lo. And בן
סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh they could be מוחל. mochal. How much
is it about they personally have been rebelled against and how much
is it about undermining the institution of, you know, parenthood, of the
authority of parents? Right? So he's saying all of those things, if
the personal people involved are מוחל, mochal, we don't step in to
protect the institution. So הגמרא ha-gemara says, וכשבאתי אצל חבריי שבדרום, u-cheshe-bati
etzel chaverai she-ba-darom,
when I came to my colleagues in the south, על שניים הודו
לי, al shnayim hodu li, they agreed with me on the two:
the parents and marriage, which are more private institutions, you know, again,
everybody in society might engage in it, but each—each instantiation is private.
There's not one for all of society. ועל זקן ממרא לא הודו
לי. ve-al zaken mamre lo hodu li. But not for זקן ממרא.
zaken mamre. שלא ירבו מחלוקת בישראל. she-lo yarbu machloket be-yisrael. That therefore,
you know, you should not allow there to be, you know, there's
got to be one final authority, one supreme court, and that has
to be protected for all of society. There's one court for all
of society, it's not their personal הקפדה. hakpada. Such a great question.
How much is protecting the institution or how much is about the
people involved? Now the interesting thing is that in the תורה, torah,
the רמב"ן ramban points this out, that four places, right, there in
פרשת שופטים, parshat shoftim, כי תצא, ki teitzei, etc., or no, it's
ראה re'eh and שופטים—anyway, shoftim four places the תורה torah says והנשארים
ישמעו וייראו, ve-ha-nish'arim yishme'u ve-yira'u, which means that the punishment is not
so much because of the gravity of... crime, but it's in order
for protecting the institution in society and that everybody else learn a
lesson. And you know what those four places are? זקן ממרא, Zaken
Mamrei, בן
סורר ומורה, Ben Sorer u'Moreh, which is the whole question, what did
the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u'Moreh do that's so bad? רמב"ן's
Ramban answer is, he didn't do anything that was so bad, but
he's threatening the institution of the authority of parents and that has
to be protected in society. עדים זוממין Eidim Zomemin that are undermining
the, you know, court system, right, you know, and they're allowing the
court to be perjured or whatever and we have to protect the
integrity of the court. And the last one is, I think is,
what is it עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachat or is it, yeah, is
it עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachat or, yeah, I think it's like the,
or is it a נביא שקר? Navi Sheker? Might be a נביא
שקר. Navi Sheker. Might be a נביא שקר Navi Sheker which is
basically God's authority. Who speaks on behalf of God? Right? So anyway,
so all of those are about protecting those institutions of authority. The
one thing that's not in that list, of course, is the one
thing that the תורה Torah makes highly subjective, about סוטה, Sotah, right?
כי יקנא איש את אשתו Ki Yikne Ish Es Ishto which is
very much about him and his jealousy. So if you ask me,
I would have said, על אחת הודו לי ועל שתים לא הודו
לי Al Achat Hodu Li V'Al Shtayim Lo Hodu Li like, by
סוטה Sotah it should be obvious that it's about הקפדת הבעל, Hakpadat
HaBa'al, right? By these other two, maybe it is more broadly about
the institution. Anyway, such a great question.
But they whispered in that the בעל Ba'al could
be—yeah, they were okay with the בעל, Ba'al, but they were also
okay with the case of בן סורר
ומורה.
Ben
Sorer u'Moreh.
Okay. Why is there another תנא—no, Tanna there isn't.
So the גמרא Gemara says, שמע מינה בעל שמחל על קינויו קינויו
מחול.
Shma
Mina
Ba'al SheMocha Al Kinnuyav, Kinnuyav Machul. You see, he can revoke it.
So contemporary, right? The whole, really, the whole Supreme Court argument was
about the institution of marriage.
Exactly. Right, about the personal rights of whatever. Yeah, exactly, very good
point. Okay, שמע מינה. Shma Mina. So good, we've proven it. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says, פליגי בה—now Paligi Ba that we've proven
that you can revoke it even for the laws of סוטה Sotah
when we're no longer talking about עוברת על דת, Overs Al Dat,
okay. פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא. Paligi Ba Rav Acha veRavina. רב
אחא Rav Acha and רבינא Ravina debate. חד אמר Chad Amar קודם
סתירה מחול, Kodem Stira Machul, ואחר סתירה אינו מחול. ve'achar stira eino
machul. That can only be before she goes in private. Because then
even the going in private loses its ef—like its meaning once he's—once
he's retracted. But after she's gone in private and you've got the
רגלים לדבר Raglayim LaDavar etc., you can't revoke, then it becomes an
objective reality. It gets into the court system as it were. That
makes to me a lot of sense. וחד אמר, Ve'chad amar, the
other says, אחר סתירה נמי מחול, Achar Stira Nami Machul, he can
even revoke it even after סתירה, Stira, which again goes back like
I said to the first question of the first משנה. Mishna. How
much is this all about the husband's jealousy and schlepping his wife
and how much is this about רגלים לדבר Raglayim LaDavar and a
case of בית דין. Beis Din. So this approach says even after
she becomes the סוטה Sotah he can just stop the whole proceedings
and revoke everything. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, מסתברא כמאן דאמר
אינו מחול. Mistabra KeMan DeAmar Eino Machul. It makes the sense that
after she goes in private he can no longer revoke. ממאי? Mi-mai?
How do you know? מדקאמרי רבנן לרבי יוסי—think Mideka'amarei Rabanan leRabbi Yosi
about the response to רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. דתניא, Detanya, we saw
this before. רבי יוסי אומר בעל נאמן עליה מקל וחומר. Rabbi Yosi
omer Ba'al Ne'eman Aleha MiKal VaChomer.
We don't need to send, you know, chaperones when they're going to
the בית דין. Beis Din. We can trust the husband not to
have sex with her on the way. ומה נדה שהיא בכרת בעל
נאמן עליה. Umah Niddah she'hi be'kares ba'al ne'eman aleha. When she's a
נדה, Niddah,
they're able to sleep together in the same room and we're not
afraid of sex and we assume we know they'll control—he'll control himself.
סוטה שהיא בלאו לא כל שכן. Sotah she'hi be'lav lo kol sheken.
How much more so will he control herself—he control himself here, you
know, which is—it's actually—it's actually could be the opposite way. He has—he'll
be less restrained because it's less severe. But how much more will
we be prepared to believe him, you know, in even in a
lesser matter. If we're prepared to believe him in a weighty matter,
we're prepared to believe him in a lesser matter. Okay, that's what
he said. אמרו
לו, Amru Lo, and they said back to him, לא. Lo. אם
אמרת בנדה שכן יש לה היתר. Im Amarta beNiddah sheken yesh lah
heter. By
a נדה, Niddah, he'll restrain himself because they'll be able to sleep
together again, you know, soon enough. תאמר בסוטה שאין לה היתר. Tomer
beSotah she'ein lah heter. But by a סוטה Sotah he won't restrain
himself because they'll never be able to sleep together. ואם אמרת אחר
סתירה מחול לה. Ve'im amarta achar stira machul lah. And now the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, if he has a way of revoking
her whole status by being מוחל Mochel on it, משכחת לה דיש
לה היתר. mishkachas lah de'yesh lah heter. So he'll also be able
to restrain himself. He'll say, I don't have to sleep with her
now, I don't have this urgency. If I ever want to sleep
with her later, I could just choose to revoke her status. So
he won't feel an urgency. Okay. דאי
בעי מחל ליה לקינויו ובעל. De'ei ba'ei machal lei le'kinnuyei u'ba'al. He
could always revoke his קינוי. Kinnuy. אלא שמע מינה, Ella shma mina,
it seems clear that once she has that status, the husband is
out of it, now it becomes a matter for the court. אלא
לאו שמע מינה אחר סתירה אינו מחול שמע מינה. Ella lav shma
mina achar stira eino machul shma mina. So it's great, so you
see that he can't. So what's great is, we actually say, is
it about the husband's jealousy or is it a matter of the
court? We say, yeah, that transition happens after the סתירה. Stira. He
warns her, she goes into סתירה Stira with—until that point it's all
about what's going on in his mind, right? But then she goes
into private, into seclusion, and there are two witnesses, then we've created
an objective רגלים לדבר Raglayim LaDavar then we as the court step
in and
say— So that would be right, so why did it have to
be Torah scholars you mean?
It's because they could...
no, so when, so now we're not saying that, that they, it's
not that they would advise him how to get around it, they
would just stop him from having sex regardless. Right, yeah.
This is the
conclusion that he can, that he can revoke before סתירה, stirah, he
can't revoke after סתירה. stirah. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this,
מתו בעליהן עד שלא שתו בית שמאי אומרים. Meisu baleinu ad shelo
shasu Beis Shammai omrim. So let's turn the page because there's so
little on the next page. מתו בעליהן עד שלא שתו בית שמאי
אומרים. Meisu baleinu ad shelo shasu Beis Shammai omrim. So here the
question is the husband died before they had a chance to drink.
Who collects the כתובה? Kesuvah? The woman, or does the woman collect
the כתובה, Kesuvah, does it remain the man's? Right? Due to nobody's
fault it is, she can't go ahead and prove her
innocence and what do you call it but and now it's time
for the כתובה Kesuvah to be collected, the husband died. Okay so
who, so who collects it? So the גמרא Gemara says, or does
she collect it? So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says she collects it
and בית הלל Beis Hillel says she doesn't collect it. במאי קמיפלגי?
Bemai kamifligi? What's the debate?
בית שמאי סברי, Beis Shammai savri, שטר העומד לגבות כגבוי דמי. shtar
ha'omed ligbos kegavui dami. Since the כתובה Kesuvah is,
is a document that's standing for collection, she's entitled to collect it,
it's like it's already collected, which means if she has an outstanding
IOU which is the כתובה, Kesuvah, an outstanding debt to her, it's
like she's in possession of the property. And if he wants to
prove that he doesn't have to pay it, he has the burden
of proof. So here it's quite interesting, you might have said what
do you mean? The fact that she's a סוטה sotah means he's
entitled to divorce her without a כתובה. Kesuvah. But the answer is
no because actually ultimately it's rooted in the question of did she
commit adultery or not? And that was a question that we could
have resolved had you lived long enough, you know, you know, that
there was a possibility of resolving. So it's interesting, the way to
determine, you didn't have to frame it this way, but the way
to determine is she entitled to the כתובה Kesuvah is not the
question is she a סוטה sotah right now and forbidden to her
husband, but it's the question of did she commit adultery? And therefore
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says well she has the presumption of being
in possession or like having you
know of the money that's owed her and if you want to
say she's not entitled to it you have to prove that she
committed adultery. Okay and בית הלל סברי Beis Hillel savri and בית
הלל Beis Hillel says the other way, שטר העומד לגבות לאו כגבוי
דמי. shtar ha'omed ligbos lav kegavui dami. No it's still he's still
considered to be the מוחזק, muchzak, the one in possession. The burden
of proof is on her, so she has to prove that she
didn't commit adultery and since she can't do that then she does
not collect her כתובה.
Kesuvah. And they have that מחלוקת בדיני ממונות machlokes bedinei mamonos independent?
Yeah so these huge תוספות-im Tosafos are trying to navigate other סוגיות
sugyos that don't exactly match up with this. It's a huge... I
understand. So you can read through these huge תוספות-im Tosafos that try
to say it's not so simple, the circumstances make a big difference
when we would and wouldn't say this, and these תוספות-im Tosafos navigate
all those different סוגיות sugyos to say you know it's not a
simple black and white type of a question. Exactly,
exactly. מעוברת חבירו, Meuberes chavaro, see this? We're going to finish the
דף. daf. Okay so the final הלכה halacha is a woman who
is
pregnant and then a... מעוברת חבירו, meuberes chavaro, the husband died, or
she's nursing and the husband died, and a man marries her. He's
not allowed to marry her within the first two years of the
child's until the child is two years old so that he shouldn't
be, so she shouldn't be disregarding the welfare of the current child
and that she'll get pregnant and won't be able to give the
right care to the current child. So that's the restriction of marrying
a woman that is pregnant or nursing another man's child. Now and
the relevance of the משנה Mishna was that if they're in that
relationship can he make her, make her drink the סוטה sotah water
or not because they're not supposed to be married but it's not
exactly the same like a negative prohibition. So right is that enough
of a of a legitimate marriage that he can make her drink
the סוטה sotah water? That was the relevance. But now we're going
to look at the issue of מעוברת חבירו. meuberes chavaro. So אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar
Avuha, מחלוקת בעקרה וזקנה. machlokes be'akarah u'zekeinah.
This debate because if you might remember there was the other position
in the משנה, Mishna, I think it was רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
who said that... oh I'm sorry I jumped to the מעוברת meuberes
case but the גמרא Gemara actually right now is focusing on an
easier case, on the case about let's say the woman is not
able to have kids. So according to the חכמים, Chachamim, well this
isn't a viable marriage, he has to divorce her. And therefore because
of that he can't make her drink the סוטה sotah water because
they need to get divorced because he needs to have the מצוה
mitzvah to have kids. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says what do
you mean? He can always just marry another woman. Yeah so why
are you calling this not a viable marriage? So that was the
debate about is it when she's not able to have kids is
that considered a legitimate viable marriage that he can make her drink
the סוטה sotah water. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, מחלוקת
בעקרה וזקנה, machlokes be'akarah u'zekeinah, the debate is a woman who is
who is like sterile, infertile, or elderly. אבל אילונית, Aval aylonis, a
woman who is born in like in a way that she sort
of never from birth never had the ability to have children, like
the גמרא Gemara describes in very male characteristics or whatever, maybe she
so maybe she didn't have a womb. uterus or other types of
things fundamentally did not was not from the birth was not able
to have kids. In
that case כולי עלמא לא פליגי kuli alma lo pligi then everybody
would agree she doesn't drink and it's not because he whether he
needs to divorce her or doesn't need to divorce her. For different
reasons she's not in the פרשה parsha of סוטה, sotah, שנאמר, shene'emar,
ונקתה ונזרעה זרע, veniketa venizre'a zara, because it ends by saying she'll
be able to bear seed. מי שדרכה להזריע, mi shedarka lehazri'a, it
only includes women that are in the פרשה parsha of having kids.
So an עקרה akarah when she was younger she could have kids,
a זקנה zekeina when she was younger she could have kids. An
עקרה akarah is seen as a like as some type of an
of like not an intrinsic problem to her very nature, you know?
It's a medical condition. You can always דאוון. daven. Exactly! But an
איילונית aylonis that's her whole category is somebody who's who can't have
kids and therefore she's excluded from the category of drinking of a
סוטה. sotah. So there's nothing to do with whether he should be
divorcing her or not divorcing her, she's fundamentally excluded. יצאה זו שאין
דרכה להזריע. yatza zo she'ein darka lehazri'a. Okay, and we will end
with that now to continue that on.